好 大家早安
Good morning
我們
這個月我們說了什麼故事
記不記得我們說了什麼故事
What story
have we learned these past months
有人知道
什麼故事
Jacob
我們學了Jacob的故事
今天我們會說Joseph
誰聽過Joseph的故事
舉手 聽過Joseph的故事
Experts
誰看過
What's that movie
Prince of Egypt
Who's watched Prince of Egypt
還有一套戲
叫
What's the new one
OK forget it
我們一起讀
Genesis chapter 37
Let's read together
Joseph a young man of 17
was tending the flocks
with his brothers
Now Israel loved Joseph
more than any of his other sons
because he had been born to him
in his old age
一起讀
and he made
an ordinate robe for him
When his brothers saw
OK
那麼Joseph
Jacob
生了多少個兒子
知道嗎
12個
Joseph排第幾
誰說12
有沒有人
有11個兄弟
姐妹
有沒有
OK
那麼Jacob
排11
但是他的
Status是怎樣
Jacob對他是怎樣
他最喜歡誰
他最喜歡
就是Joseph
我們怎知道他最喜歡Joseph
他給了他什麼
一個Robe
我們看下一頁
他很漂亮的一個Robe
彩色的
可能彩色
很漂亮的一個Robe
OK
他
他爸爸給了他
那麼漂亮的一個Robe
他哥哥又怎樣
就開始不喜歡他
是不是
之前我們說
They could not speak a kind word to him
They hated him
你們
誰有弟兄姊妹
你覺得你是不是
Keep your hand raised
誰有弟兄姊妹
OK
誰覺得自己是favorite
Keep your hands raised
Timon你都沒有
你有嗎 你有
OK
你覺得你是favorite
你的感受是怎樣
是很開心還是不喜歡
Timon你喜歡還是不喜歡
喜歡
有沒有人不喜歡他是favorite
OK
誰覺得自己不是favorite
沒有人
個個都覺得自己是favorite
OK
Winnie也是
No
你覺得You are not the favorite
我媽媽疼兒子
哦
媽媽疼兒子 有沒有人好像
Auntie Winnie那樣
OK Bobby
你也是兒子
哦
你媽媽喜歡姐姐多一點
OK
但媽媽喜歡你是不是
不知道 OK
你回去問一下
那這個story呢
Jacob favor了Joseph
後果是甚麼
favoritism causes envy
那些哥哥呢
就很憎Joseph
是不是
Joseph是很high的
Oh he is the loved one
他爸爸最喜歡他的
但都是很low
因為
他的哥哥對他不好
是不是
他對他不可以說一個好的說話
Can't speak a kind word to him
這個是我
有沒有兄弟姐妹
沒有
沒有兄弟姐妹
我只有我自己一個
所以我沒有
experience這個favoritism
因為我經常都是favorite
好像
single child
有沒有single child
You are the favorite
No choice
但我剛剛去了一個婚禮
在這個婚禮
她的爸爸
這個爸爸就說
這個
結婚的妹妹
就是她的favorite
有沒有去過婚禮
知不知道
亂說話
我不知道
這個大女兒有什麼感受
有沒有少少envy
不知道
可能那個家庭很loving
It doesn't matter
Ok
不單止她是favorite
我們繼續看這個story
她有
Joseph 做夢
昨晚誰睡覺有做過夢
有做夢
Joseph 做夢什麼
踢球嗎
不是 是女孩
不用說
我們看看Joseph
做夢做了什麼
Let's read together
1,2,3
I had a dream
All of your stacks of wheat
made a circle around mine
and bowed down to it
有多少個stack of wheat
知不知道
Yes 12 stacks of wheat
是不是
有12個兄弟
接著那些stack of wheat 怎樣
bowed down towards
the one
他還有一個dream
我們一起讀
next dream
Let's read together 1,2,3
Another dream
The sun, the moon
and the 11 stars
bowing down to me
不單止
星星是誰
11個星星是誰
對了 兄弟
那太陽呢
和月亮是誰
可能他爸爸
是不是
那你覺得
兄弟有什麼反應
他是favorite
接著呢 現在又
做夢 做夢 這些東西
他有什麼反應呢
Do you think this means
you will be king
and rule over us
他這個哥呢
就很生氣 罵他
是不是 搞錯
你覺得我 你會做
我的王 是不是
他爸爸都罵他
搞錯 你為什麼會這樣說的
是不是
那
我之前都做夢 是不是
我之前 我們看那個next slide
有沒有人看到
很特別的東西 這個slide
有什麼在這
有沒有看到什麼
什麼
田邦看到什麼
誰來的
什麼來的
左手邊是什麼來的
看到什麼
看不到 誰看不到
什麼來的
蜘蛛俠來的
Yeah did you see
Spiderman right there
我們打波的時候
在維園 接著呢
旁邊有個Spiderman在這
我告訴你 我有一次
做夢 我做夢我是什麼
我是Spiderman
我是Spiderman 我在New York
我在紐約
是不是紐約
那New York就有一個
terrorist attack
It's in the subway system
There is a subway attack
Do you know how the terrorist attack
怎麼attack subway system
知不知道
他是用什麼 用肥皂
He flooded
The metro with soap
那些soap繼續
Rising
那我做蜘蛛俠
就救人
扔人出去
Metro
Ok 接著呢
那些soap 肥皂
Keep rising
很高
接著我快要
Drown的時候
I'm getting drown by soap
我還沒drown的時候
神啊 幫幫我
And then I woke up
That was my dream
那如果我告訴你這個夢
你會不會覺得 嘩 這個Johnny
搞錯啊 他以為他自己是蜘蛛俠嗎
是不是
是不是 會不會
Maybe
可能Joseph
不是想自己promote
自己的 他覺得
嘩 神給了我這個dream
他只是想去分享
神給他的dream
但是這首歌
怎麼看這個dream
這首歌怎麼看這個dream
他看到他們
他看到Joseph
好像很驕傲
Prideful 覺得他自己
威過他們這首歌
Ok
We're gonna skip the verses
We're gonna go self-promotion
Displeasure
Self-promotion causes displeasure
在這個situation
Joseph share
他的dream
這首歌就覺得
嘩
這個Joseph
不單是一個favorite
覺得他自己會做王
會rule over us
你們身邊
有沒有人是
很self-promote自己
嘩 這個人很厲害
這個人很厲害
讀書很厲害
有沒有人覺得有些friend
很self-promotion
Self-promote自己
你們在笑嗎
有個同學是這樣
Bobby也是這樣
有個friend
他是怎樣的
自己很瘦
但是
但是他不瘦
他是瘦
他稱讚自己很瘦
很有肌肉
他講
你不知道但是他講
Ok
第二個high是什麼
嘩 Joseph看到
有個dream
神可能跟他說話
這個dream
這個dream是
about what
他的understanding
他是很high
他receive到一個dream
from god
有沒有人做夢
覺得神跟他說話
through this dream
有沒有人
你知不知道在
Dimussilam
的country
有時神跟他說話
知不知道怎樣跟他說話
Do you know how
God has been speaking to some Muslims
through what
through dreams
dreams about
Jesus
imagine
you don't know the truth your whole life
you've been taught something different
and then you have
a dream
and in this dream
Jesus reveals himself
as lord
and savior
that would change
your life
Ok我們繼續看
Let's read together
next slide 123
Here comes Joseph
the dreamer
we should kill him now while we can
繼續
Let's not kill him
we can put him
into a well
without hurting him
they attacked him
and tore off his long
and beautiful coat
then they threw him into an empty well
that was dry
when the media knights
traders
came by
the brothers took Joseph out
of the well and sold him
the traders
who brought Joseph down
bought Joseph
took him down to Egypt
Wow
Joseph
被他的哥哥
出賣
有一日他爸爸
你去找你哥哥吧
他的哥哥不知道去了哪裡
他們做什麼
做什麼工作他們之前
herding sheep
他的哥哥
看到他自己一個
爸爸不在身邊
他就找這個機會
出賣他
是不是
想殺死他
他的哥哥Ruben
就說不要殺死他
give mercy upon him
不要
hurt他
然後他就賣了他
去埃及
anybody
nobody
這個叫Rock Bottom
你想一下Joseph的感受
是什麼
他之前是什麼
the favorite
可能有什麼好吃呢
爸爸都給他
爸爸照顧他
他living a good life
可能一個good life
I am not exactly sure
但接著
是Rock Bottom
被哥哥出賣了
他的衣服又拿了
是不是
他被人
扔了在一個
Citroen
有沒有人見過一個well
anybody been to a well
no, is it deep
你去過
我想這個Citroen有多deep
接著他被人賣了
有沒有人看過gladiator
gladiator the movie
yeah
do you remember he was being sold
and carried
好像這樣
被人carry, sold
to a different place
and he was being sold
to become a gladiator
我以前有一個
很好的兄弟
他就畢業
waterloo畢業
都幾聰明
接著會有一個job在google
no, not google, apple
做什麼
做一個quality control
幫China
看ipad的quality
他沒有的
他有幾型的
他有這架車
let's look at the next slide
he had this car
does anybody know what car it is
什麼車來的,有沒有人知道
之前呢
這個車幾型的
叫做Honda, yes
Honda Integra
type R, ok
現在都有的,但新款
他有這架車,他就會搬去
就快搬去美國
去apple做full time
他在多倫多住,他就說
我會賣車
他就說
你想不想買
我就說
我當然想
有一個這麼型的車
棍波
it's gonna be so cool
有沒有人想
有一個型車
Winston之前有很多車
很多車,我知道你
你之前說了很多車
我就說
I am so excited
我要一個好型的車
可以drive around and everything
然後我們已經說了
價錢
你想什麼價
ok,這個價,ok
然後呢
我已經買了
有些interior
因為已經覺得
快要給我車
有一天
他message我,他就說
Johnny
I mean no disrespect
But
I have to give my car to the mechanic
Because he helped me
build the car
我心想
No disrespect
ok
但我們已經說了價錢
是不是
I feel a bit betrayed
I felt a bit betrayed
Hi
If you are listening to this sermon
It's your car
I felt betrayed
但這個是車
是不是
I don't own the car
但Joseph
他給11個兄弟
出賣他
不單止出賣
Egypt
當是好像
Nothing product
sold
是不是
20 pieces of silver
你覺得你自己
Worth多少錢
是不是20 pieces of silver
You think you are worth 20 pieces of silver
No, maybe gold, right
Not silver, gold
ok
我們繼續讀story
我們這次讀中文
你幫我讀中文
1,2,3
繼續
Next slide
最後
好
Joseph
被人賣了去埃及
他去了埃及
去了誰的家
Potiphar
知道Potiphar做什麼嗎
知道嗎
有人知道Potiphar做什麼嗎
He was in charge of
the guards, I think
He was in charge of the Pharaoh's guards
Ok, something like that
他去到
Potiphar的家
然後怎麼樣,是不是很慘
是不是好像Cinderella
經常要
做家務
是不是很慘
不是,神怎麼樣
神祝福他
He was the next high
Found favor in Potiphar's eyes
Potiphar
給了他
這個Joseph
很聰明
我就給了他
take care 整間屋
everything
He entrusted everything
he owned to his care
因為Joseph
整間屋
都有祝福
神祝福了整間屋
Potiphar paid no attention
to anything
except the food
that he ate
神祝福了Joseph
祝福了
Potiphar整間屋
但是
有個high
然後會有什麼
有low
sometimes that's life
有high
有low
low是什麼呢
Joseph
的老婆
就看到他
Joseph你都幾靚仔
又
又well built
這個
Potiphar的老婆
就看到他
你
有沒有興趣
是不是這樣問的
我不知道
有沒有興趣
是不是
他就想和她
She wanted to sleep with him
Right
那Joseph怎樣
Joseph說
No
是不是
No thank you
為什麼No
He said
Let's go to chapter 39
With me in charge
My master does not concern himself
with anything in the house
Next slide
No one is greater in this house than I am
My master has
with nothing from me
except you because you are his wife
How then
could I do such a wicked thing
and sin
against God
Joseph說
我怎樣可以
對神
犯罪
不單止是得罪
Potiphar我怎樣可以
對神
犯罪
接著怎樣
有一日
Potiphar的老婆
就說
進來房間清潔這個東西
是不是
一清潔的時候
他就說你和我在這裡
Lie down
Come lie down
接著Joseph怎樣
Joseph就
立即走了
立即閃了
但他留了什麼
他留了他的
他的cloak
He left his cloak
那老婆就用這個cloak
去accuse他
Potiphar
你這個slave
你請回來的這個slave
你看看他想做什麼
是不是
接著他就扔了Joseph
坐牢
It's funny
I just thought of it
Joseph had a beautiful coat
It was stripped
And now somebody
Tried to take him
And he left his coat
What do you think it means
Interesting
我們看到三樣東西
Favoritism leads to
Envy
Self promotion leads to
Displeasure
Rejection
Leads to offense
Rejection leads to offense
Potiphar's wife wrongfully accuses
Joseph
He sets him up
And he is thrown in jail
很嗨
接著又很老
And when he was thrown into prison
Once again
他坐了牢的時候
神又祝福他
他又in charge of everything
在prison那裡
Warden
in charge of everything
神給他有success
他做什麼
都有success
God blessed him
我們這個story of Joseph
我們學到什麼
What can we learn from the story of Joseph
第一是faithfulness
Faithfulness 中文是什麼
中心
中心對不對
Loyalty
信實
Faithfulness
他對誰是faithful
第一他對他爸爸是faithful
He is faithfully tending the flock
Faithfully taking care of the house
他爸爸叫他去找他哥
他就去找他哥
He is faithful to his father
之後
他被人出賣
He is faithful to Potiphar
他做到
Potiphar 看到他
嘩這麼聰明
我給他所有
整間屋
給他in charge
in prison he was also
faithful to the warden
and most importantly
他是faithful to God
faithful to God
Potiphar's wife
他想試探他
sleep with him
他認得
神
是最重要的
我不可以
犯罪
Do this wicked thing against God
He was faithful
Because he was faithful
He was blessed
神就祝福他
是不是
神祝福他
他有很多low
很多low periods
被人出賣
但神都protect了他
之前的哥
想殺死他
但大哥就說
不要
我們就這樣扔他
這個well 就可以了
God protected him
in the most difficult times
他被人
扔了去Egypt
埃及
神又provide給他
他被人扔了去監獄
神都繼續
祝福他
We see God's blessing
throughout the story of Joseph
Because he was faithful
faithful in every situation
and ultimately
faithful to God
最後
第三點
next slide
God's plan
We know that God has a plan
and later in the story
we see that Joseph rises
to become second in command
in Egypt
second in command
Joseph 有沒有
搞錯
你對我這麼差
他有沒有complain
He didn't complain
Joseph 可以give up
給一些家人
給一些哥出賣我
我不做了
我不跟隨你了
He could have given up
He could have complained against God
But he didn't
Today he knew that this dream
was God speaking to him
And that God had a plan
OK
我們現在邀請Kristen上來
去講見證
我們給一點掌聲她
我是Kristen
我今年Grade 11
即是4.5
我從二年級開始來這個Church
So it's been some time
Pastor Johnny
想我和大家分享一下
我怎樣在困難當中
去經歷
其實我是一個比較喜歡自己
go through things的一個人
我很少會和別人分享
我經歷的困難
因為我經常覺得
as long as I do all the best
I can control the end result
and achieve what I want to achieve
但變了我經常很專注
我要做的事
and achieve my goal
變了我很少留下空間
讓我自己去rest
and also to quiet down
變了sadly我經常忘記了
我可以分享一下
我過去的幾個禮拜
For me
相信和大家一樣
都是比較tough
for me 是蠻困難
and also sometimes I felt a bit sad
因為有很多deadlines and commitments
經常夾在
兩件事的中間
and that's a story for another day
但是
有complication of things
加起來就變成這樣
and something that troubles me the most
就是thinking about uni
because you know junior year
開始plan for university
想讀什麼
我的朋友他們全部都是
有很大的goals
and 他們想做的事都是
蠻high achieving的
他們就開始說
他們想做的事
他們想take a course
and 他們的test score都蠻高
and compare to me
他們take a course is more challenging
because we are doing different things
但是
他跟我說
我的course ok
變成我經常很怕我的course
and the things I do
aren't enough
變成我最後做了
committed myself to a lot of different things
which 變成
I stressed myself too much
現在我經常覺得
if I'm not doing enough
那可能我的application for senior year
是不夠competitive
and
因為我take a course
跟其他人是不一樣
and 有時
during the past week
I've been doubted if I'm even fit for
the course that I want to apply next year
因為我經常覺得
我做得不夠好
and 這樣東西
令我是pretty sad
因為我不知道我還可以做些什麼
因為if I go back now
it's a bit too late
because everything is pretty much set halfway
and sadly
despite all these difficulties
他們都沒有忘記我
he surrounded me with different friends
他們會經常send me worship songs
and bible verses
我跟他說很多東西
他們都不會try to solve my problem
but instead
他會send me bible verses
是挺comforting
reminded me that I'm not going through everything alone
我們更加不是
defined by我們在人生中
所做的事
or achieve的事
我們太大太小
被神
take care for我們
a few weeks back
我們有一個東西在學校
我們就唱了一首worship song
叫come away
歌詞挺好的
it says come away with me
it's never too late
it's not too late
I have a plan for you
it's gonna be wild
it's gonna be great
他reminded me
神是掌管一切的
他永遠有一個plan for you
and it's always gonna be best
他也永遠會在那裡等你
to welcome you back
no matter what happens
所以當我們去尋求神的時候
他會給我們平安和comfort
他的計劃是遠超過我們所想和所求的
one thing that I found really helpful
was to keep a prayer journal
at that time and time
你可能不會發覺
為什麼那樣東西會發生
我們也不會明白
為什麼他會想你去做那樣東西
或那樣東西為什麼會
like happen
但是當你回頭去看的時候
你就會看到神
他為什麼每一步
他帶領你去
他想你去的地方
他給你的計劃
and who he wants you to be and go
it's not like I have
everything figured out
因為我們每一個人都還在學習
怎麼去更加的
依賴神
我希望我今天的分享可以鼓勵大家
as we go through things together
and to經歷神更多
I will end with a bible verse
如果你認識我的話
這是我one of my favorite bible verses
it's from Jeremiah 29.11
it says
For I know the plans I have for you declares the Lord
plans to prosper you and not to harm you
plans to give you a hope and a future
(掌聲)
He was faithful
He was faithful as a son
to the task that he was given
When he was in Potiphar's house
He was faithful
to what his master had given him
When he was in jail
He was faithful
Are we faithful
to God what He has given us
What has God given you
And are you faithful
Maybe it's your studies
Maybe it's your career
Maybe it's the friends that He has given you
Maybe it's your son or daughter
Maybe it's family
Are you faithful
Are you faithful to Him
And are you
Faithful to God ultimately
Next is
Do we want to be blessed
Who wants to be blessed here
Nobody wants to be blessed
Who wants to be blessed
How do you become blessed by God
Joseph 怎樣呀
他做咩都有success
我哋點可以咁樣呀
How can we have
The same blessing that Joseph has
Can we
得唔得呀
得唔得
邊個覺得得嘅舉手
Ok 冇人覺得得呀
真係
真係覺得唔得
Wow
How do we be blessed
By God
Psalm 1 says this
He who meditates on the word of God
Day and night
He's like a tree
Planted by streams of water
Which produces its fruit in season
And whatever he does
He prospers
Psalm 1 tells us that we need to meditate
And focus on the word of God
And then whatever we do
That's God's promise
That we would prosper
我哋點可以
俾神去祝福我哋呀
The key is this
To put him first
In your studies
Put him first
You want God to bless you in your studies
Trust in God
To help you
Put him first
You want God to bless your finances
Give him a portion of what you have first
You want God to bless your relationships
Put him first in your relationship
Put him first
And you will be blessed
By God
The blessing might not be what you expect
But it will be God's will for you
And what he believes is best
And the last thing is this
Do we trust God's plan?
我哋信唔相信
神係佢有自己既旨意
Just like Kristen, right?
佢有時有high
讀書有時有low
She goes through ups and downs
你個個都go through ups and downs
Me too
But do we believe God has a plan?
即使Kristen讀書有low passage
Jeremiah
God has a plan for us
To prosper
In the midst of difficult times
Maybe we're betrayed
Maybe we've been let down
Maybe we've failed
Do we still believe
God has a plan?
And if we trust him
If we obey him
If we are faithful
God will lead us through
我之前share咗一個story
係一個弟兄
應該賣咗架車俾我嘅
但係冇賣到
So there's another story
Another car here
This next car
有冇人知咩車黎架
It's a Lexus
IS 250 F Sport
呢個朋友係Taiwanese
個friend黎架
咁佢又係Waterloo
讀過喎
咁佢讀完書呢
佢畢咗業呢
佢就話Johnny啊
我返去台灣啦
I don't know what I'm saying
I'm going back to Taiwan
Do you want my car?
咁我話咩啊
What do you think I said
Yes, sure, I want your car
Will you sell it to me?
咁佢同我講嘅時呢
我就諗起之前
有人話賣架車俾我
但係之後呢冇賣到
But this time
He sold it to me
And on December 10th
I'm gonna go back to Toronto
And I'm gonna drive my car
And I will see you in February
When I come back
This is my way of telling you
I'll be gone for a little bit
But that God will still bless us
God takes
God gives
Still
Blessed be the name of the Lord
Let's pray together
As the worship team comes up
Heavenly Father
We thank you for the story of Joseph
He experienced many highs
He experienced many lows
But in the midst of them all
He was faithful to you
He obeyed you
In everything that he did
And that he was blessed
And I pray that for each one of us
That even in the midst of our highs
It may be really good marks
It may be really low marks
It may be failures
That we would still trust you
And that you would bless us
Because we trust
That you have a plan for us
And that you will guide us
In the way that we should go
祝福我們,主耶穌,我們祈禱在耶穌的名下。